<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Long COVID | Corona Data Donation Project | News &amp; Analyses</title>
    <link>https://corona-datenspende.github.io/en/category/long-covid/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://corona-datenspende.github.io/en/category/long-covid/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Long COVID</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://corona-datenspende.github.io/media/logo_hu67c7d7cb86270e1a53c42ee36a2e3695_20109_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>Long COVID</title>
      <link>https://corona-datenspende.github.io/en/category/long-covid/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Our data donation roadmap for 2023</title>
      <link>https://corona-datenspende.github.io/en/reports/kickoff-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://corona-datenspende.github.io/en/reports/kickoff-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dear data donors,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are part of what is one of the world&amp;rsquo;s largest citizen science projects in public health research. Over 540,000 people from across Germany have participated since April 2020, for more than 120,000 individuals we were able to gather comprehensive &lt;a href=&#34;https://corona-datenspende.github.io/en/vitaldata-tool/&#34;&gt;records of resting pulse, daily activity, and sleep duration&lt;/a&gt; over a span of 2.5 years. Using specialized algorithms, our &lt;a href=&#34;https://corona-datenspende.github.io/en/reports/monitor/&#34;&gt;Fever Monitor and Nowcast&lt;/a&gt; have processed up to 120 million physiological and behavioral data points each day to detect anomalous movement and pulse patterns in the population and provide insights into real-time tracking the spread of possible infections with SARS-CoV-2. This data set, together with psychosocial data obtained from questionnaires, is well-suited to address a wide-variety of questions regarding the COVID-19 pandemic. For us to be able to make the most of this unique data set, we &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rki.de/DE/Content/InfAZ/N/Neuartiges_Coronavirus/Corona-Datenspende-allgemein.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;suspended&lt;/a&gt; active data collection as of December 31, 2022 in order to focus our efforts on diving deeper in our analyses. Your contributions have made this project a landmark milestone in bridging the gap between science and society, and we would like to thank you for that. As this stage of the project comes to a close, our team now shifts focus onto quantitatively evaluating the fever algorithm and comprehensively investigating the long-term consequences of the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;time-for-a-general-inspection&#34;&gt;Time for a general inspection&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent advancements in research technology, of which wearable-based monitoring your vital signs is one, usher a new age of digital health in biomedical research. These developments give rise to rapid changes, not only in the tools and approaches available to researchers, but also in the ways in which research is conducted. However, left unchecked, this rapid rate of scientific progress can lead to problems in reproducibility and validity. As such, after more than two years of active field operation, we are now subjecting our fever algorithm to a comprehensive evaluation assessing its validity as a real-time monitoring system for disease detection. To this end, we will be discussing methods and results of our work with the scientific community, taking into account the findings and frameworks of similar efforts such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://detect.scripps.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;findings from abroad&lt;/a&gt;. This enables us to evaluate the potential of our fever algorithm to be used as a sensor-based monitoring tool in future pandemics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure id=fever_curve&gt;
	&lt;div id=&#34;fever_curve-display&#34; class=&#34;panel-display&#34;&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
	
 	&lt;figcaption&gt;
 		&lt;div class=&#34;pa4 tl f3 lh-copy&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fig. 1&lt;/strong&gt;: Up-to-date version of the fever algorithm. If a person&amp;rsquo;s resting heart rate and step count deviate significantly from their baseline measurements and run counter to each other (&lt;a href=&#34;%28https://corona-datenspende.github.io/en/reports/fevercurve/%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;fever bump&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;), the algorithm signals a potential infection.&lt;/div&gt;	
 	&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;keeping-an-eye-on-the-pandemics-long-term-consequences&#34;&gt;Keeping an eye on the pandemic’s long-term consequences&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other major focus in the coming months is the analysis of the &amp;ldquo;Long COVID and Pandemic Consequences&amp;rdquo; study launched in April 2022. We seek to gain a better understanding of the dynamics of changes in vital signs following infection with SARS-CoV-2, including the nature and magnitude of observed changes, time it takes to return to pre-disease baseline levels, what factors or circumstances might delay in this normalization, and potential consequences thereof. Initial analyses have already been presented to you in one of our &lt;a href=&#34;https://corona-datenspende.github.io/en/reports/breakthroughinfections/&#34;&gt;past blogposts&lt;/a&gt;. In addition,, we will investigate questionnaire data in relation to vital signs. For example, is it possible to identify physiological correlates of self-reported quality of life by analyzing patterns in resting heart rate, activity, and sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;  &lt;!-- insert blank line before figure --&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-fig-2-in-donors-with-confirmed-covid-19-infection-it-takes-about-2-3-months-for-the-resting-pulse-to-return-to-normal-in-2023-we-plan-to-investigate-this-finding-in-more-detail-especially-with-regard-to-the-reported-health-related-quality-of-life&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://corona-datenspende.github.io/reports/prolongedchanges&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;**Fig. 2**: In donors with confirmed COVID-19 infection, it takes about 2-3 months for the resting pulse to return to normal. In 2023, we plan to investigate this finding in more detail, especially with regard to the reported health-related quality of life.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/figures/prolonged_changes/vitals_65_de_hu8dc088bcc61666e02b89fbe06c1f7477_189544_a0fbaf479250ed2311e0dab904b25bf1.webp 400w,
               /media/figures/prolonged_changes/vitals_65_de_hu8dc088bcc61666e02b89fbe06c1f7477_189544_e7699b40f580c462667c91a6ebd90c9c.webp 760w,
               /media/figures/prolonged_changes/vitals_65_de_hu8dc088bcc61666e02b89fbe06c1f7477_189544_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://corona-datenspende.github.io/media/figures/prolonged_changes/vitals_65_de_hu8dc088bcc61666e02b89fbe06c1f7477_189544_a0fbaf479250ed2311e0dab904b25bf1.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;60%&#34;
               height=&#34;596&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Fig. 2&lt;/strong&gt;: In donors with confirmed COVID-19 infection, it takes about 2-3 months for the resting pulse to return to normal. In 2023, we plan to investigate this finding in more detail, especially with regard to the reported health-related quality of life.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;read-the-latest-news-on-the-blog&#34;&gt;Read the latest news on the blog&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2023, the scientific work will continue unchanged even without further data collection. On the one hand, we will strenghten collaborations with various research groups to further develop our methodology; on the other hand, we continue to engage in better understanding vital parameters and different long-term consequences of the pandemic. To that end, we will remain active on this blog and familiar channels. We are looking forward to share our research progress with you!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The data donation project launches Long COVID study</title>
      <link>https://corona-datenspende.github.io/en/reports/longcovidlaunch/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://corona-datenspende.github.io/en/reports/longcovidlaunch/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Donors,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For almost two years now, your data has helped us to better understand the course of the COVID-19 pandemic. For this, we would like to thank you once again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this time, we have learned that there is a great willingness to support science and research with health data from fitness trackers and smartwatches. Over 500,000 people have donated their vital data for at least a certain period of time and more than 38,000 people already regularly participate in our in-app surveys. Using your data, we were able to capture anomalies in vital data that is potentially related to COVID-19 symptoms and the frequency of those detections in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://corona-datenspende.github.io/en/monitor/&#34;&gt;fever monitor&lt;/a&gt; maps well to the pandemic&amp;rsquo;s waves of infection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;keeping-an-eye-on-the-long-term-consequences-of-the-pandemic&#34;&gt;Keeping an eye on the long-term consequences of the pandemic&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2022, we are expanding the focus of our research and examine the long-term health consequences of COVID-19. In the coming months, we would like to investigate, among other things, how physical activity, sleep, fitness and mental health develop in individuals after the disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this reason, &lt;strong&gt;we will launch a new study on Long COVID in the data donation app&lt;/strong&gt; which is developed in close collaboration with the Long COVID group at the Robert Koch Institute. By answering monthly questionnaires, you will help us to understand potential long-term changes in vital signs after a SARS-CoV-2 infection, to determine the frequency of long-lasting or emerging symptoms, and also study the interaction between the two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;new-research-questions-thanks-to-comprehensive-vital-data&#34;&gt;New research questions thanks to comprehensive vital data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From your donated data we have already gained important insights into the potential changes of vital signs following the acute phase of COVID-19. In one of our &lt;a href=&#34;https://corona-datenspende.github.io/en/reports/prolongedchanges/&#34;&gt;recent blogposts&lt;/a&gt;, we were able to show that the average daily resting heart rate in COVID-19 positive individuals is elevated for months following an infection and normalizations may only happen slowly (Fig. 1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;  &lt;!-- insert blank line before figure --&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-figure-1-average-change-in-daily-resting-heart-rate-for-covid-19-positive-individuals-regardless-of-vaccination-status-using-data-until-october-2021-details-on-the-calculation-and-results-can-be-found-hereenreportsprolongedchanges&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;**Figure 1:** Average change in daily resting heart rate for COVID-19 positive individuals regardless of vaccination status using data until October 2021. Details on the calculation and results can be found [here](/en/reports/prolongedchanges/).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/figures/prolonged_changes/vitals_65_en_hu8dc088bcc61666e02b89fbe06c1f7477_191228_ca2544cd0fe5887a09e62d4c0c040484.webp 400w,
               /media/figures/prolonged_changes/vitals_65_en_hu8dc088bcc61666e02b89fbe06c1f7477_191228_dadd2c827d8ec594a2be248c507bed23.webp 760w,
               /media/figures/prolonged_changes/vitals_65_en_hu8dc088bcc61666e02b89fbe06c1f7477_191228_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://corona-datenspende.github.io/media/figures/prolonged_changes/vitals_65_en_hu8dc088bcc61666e02b89fbe06c1f7477_191228_ca2544cd0fe5887a09e62d4c0c040484.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;60%&#34;
               height=&#34;596&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1:&lt;/strong&gt; Average change in daily resting heart rate for COVID-19 positive individuals regardless of vaccination status using data until October 2021. Details on the calculation and results can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://corona-datenspende.github.io/en/reports/prolongedchanges/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;!-- insert blank line before figure --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, in preliminary analyses, we found that vaccinations can have a strong positive effect on the normalization of vital signs after contracting COVID-19 (Fig. 2). You can also find these results in one of our recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://corona-datenspende.github.io/en/reports/breakthroughinfections/&#34;&gt;blogposts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;  &lt;!-- insert blank line before figure --&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-figure-2-average-change-in-resting-heart-rate-weekly-aggregates-for-covid-19-positive-individuals-who-bt-the-time-of-infection-were-either-unvaccinated-red-or-at-least-fully-vaccinated-purple-results-are-based-on-data-collected-until-january-2022-full-details-about-this-analysis-are-found-hereenreportsbreakthroughinfections&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;**Figure 2:** Average change in resting heart rate (weekly aggregates) for COVID-19 positive individuals who bt the time of infection were either unvaccinated (red) or at least fully vaccinated (purple). Results are based on data collected until January 2022. Full details about this analysis are found [here](/en/reports/breakthroughinfections/).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/figures/vaccinations/vaccines_long_covid_65_hu06435cb7b43c9780d26f4326971c5fb1_147860_3b7f6223d192ce69bafdddd18988ce7d.webp 400w,
               /media/figures/vaccinations/vaccines_long_covid_65_hu06435cb7b43c9780d26f4326971c5fb1_147860_2e97e6246b3e73e03659bb311da37efd.webp 760w,
               /media/figures/vaccinations/vaccines_long_covid_65_hu06435cb7b43c9780d26f4326971c5fb1_147860_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://corona-datenspende.github.io/media/figures/vaccinations/vaccines_long_covid_65_hu06435cb7b43c9780d26f4326971c5fb1_147860_3b7f6223d192ce69bafdddd18988ce7d.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;60%&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Figure 2:&lt;/strong&gt; Average change in resting heart rate (weekly aggregates) for COVID-19 positive individuals who bt the time of infection were either unvaccinated (red) or at least fully vaccinated (purple). Results are based on data collected until January 2022. Full details about this analysis are found &lt;a href=&#34;https://corona-datenspende.github.io/en/reports/breakthroughinfections/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;!-- insert blank line before figure --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From here, there are many other questions that we want to look at in the following months and that you can help us understand better. This includes, among others:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the long-term effects of pandemic-related behavior change on the health-related quality of life?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How long do people have diminished physical or mental capacity after being sick with COVID-19?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much do Long COVID symptoms, such as fatigue (persistent exhaustion), affect the activity and sleep patterns of recovered people?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;study-starts-on-april-4-2022&#34;&gt;Study starts on April 4, 2022&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new &lt;strong&gt;Long COVID study&lt;/strong&gt; is expected to be available in the Data Donation app on April 4. All donors will be notified via push notification once participation is open. New donors can find the app in the app stores of &lt;a href=&#34;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=de.rki.coronadatenspende&amp;amp;hl=de&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://apps.apple.com/de/app/corona-datenspende/id1504705422&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Apple&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://appgallery.huawei.com/app/C104457185&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Huawei&lt;/a&gt;. To sign up for the study, you need to first add the study via the main menu, and then elect to participate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;monthly questionnaires&lt;/strong&gt; will only take a few minutes to complete. Already now, we like to thank all donors for their continued participation and support. As usual, we will share our results with you in this blog on a regular basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have not yet participated in our other sub-studies (&lt;strong&gt;Test, Symptoms and Life Situation&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Experience and Behavior in the Pandemic&lt;/strong&gt;), we would like to invite you to participate in these surveys as well. Consent for participation in those studies is also possible through the data donation app.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
